Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Records
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Records.
1949-2001.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Connecticut Civil Liberties Union.
23 linear feet.
The Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Records document the activities, history and administrative records of this organization. The collection contains the organizational documents of the New Haven Civil Liberties Council (1949-1958), administrative records of the CCLU (1958-1990) as well as the organization's materials pertaining to court cases.
MSS19980291
History
The Connecticut affiliate of the American Civil Liberties Union, the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union (CCLU) was founded in 1949 as the New Haven Civil Liberties Council. The CCLU is a non-partisan, non-profit organization whose mission is to assure that the Bill of Rights and the rights guaranteed by the Connecticut Constitution are preserved.
Scope and Content
The Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Records document the activities, history and administrative records of this organization. The collection contains the organizational documents of the New Haven Civil Liberties Council (1949-1958), administrative records of the CCLU (1958-1990) as well as the organization's materials pertaining to the court cases, Women's Health Services v. Maher (1979-1981), Doe v. Maher (1981-1990) and Sheff v. O'Neill (1989-1998). Material pertaining to the three court cases consists primarily of court documents, trail transcripts, exhibits, correspondence and research.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut history and school desegregation, see especially the Connecticut School Desegregation Collection. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
Series I: New Haven Civil Liberties Council ( 1949-1958 ) contains documents pertaining to the founding of the organization in Connecticut.
Series II: Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Administrative Records ( undated, 1958-1990 ) includes reports, correspondence and publications documenting a portion of the organziation's activities.
Series III: Women's Health Services v. Maher ( undated, 1979-1981 ) contains the legal files pertaining to this court case concerning the legality of abortions in Connecticut.
Series IV: Doe v. Maher ( undated, 1981-1990 ) contains the legal files pertaining to this court case which continued the case begun in Women's Health Services v. Maher.
Series V: Sheff v. O'Neill ( undated, 1989-1998 ) contains the legal files pertaining to this court case regarding the desegregation of Connecticut's public schools.
Series VI: American Civil Liberties Union materials ( undated, 1954-1981 ) includes a small number of ACLU publications and similar materials.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Organizations:
Places:
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Press releases.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Interviews.; Lawsuits.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.
Occupations:
Restrictions on Access
Researchers interested in the collection must complete an CCLU Access Agreement before access to the collection will be granted.
Materials identified by the donor as "Attorney work product" is restricted material until 2006. These documents have been removed from the collection and placed in a secure location. Permission from the donor must be obtained to review the restricted material until that date.
Detailed Description
- Series I: New Haven Civil Liberties Council, 1949-1958
  - Affiliate Letter, 1949 (Box 1:1)
  - New Haven Civil Liberties Council, 1949-1958 (Box 1:2)
- Series II: Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Administrative Records, undated, 1958-1990
  - By-laws, undated (Box 1:3)
  - Church-State Committee, 1963, 1967 (Box 1:4)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1981 (Box 1:5)
  - Correspondence: ACLU, 1953, 1976 (Box 1:6)
  - Deadly Force, undated (Box 1:7)
  - Directory, 1964-1970 (Box 1:8)
  - Education, 1964 (Box 1:9)
  - Executive Director's Report, 1972-1979 (Box 1:10)
  - Legal cases
    - Campos v. Manson, 1980 (Box 1:11)
    - McMahon v. Board of Selectmen, 1980 (Box 1:12)
    - Villafane v. Manson, 197? (Box 1:13)
  - Legal Director's Report, 1972, 1979 (Box 1:14)
  - Litigation Policy, undated (Box 1:15)
  - Minutes, 1966-1980 (Box 1:16)
  - News, 1958-1982 (Box 1:17)
  - People's Rights, 1983, 1990 (Box 1:18)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1960-1965 (Box 1:19)
  - Vietnam, 1967 (Box 1:20)
- Series III: Women's Health Services v. Maher, undated, 1977-1981
  - Court Documents
    - Motion to Remand, undated (Box 2:21)
    - Temporary Injunction and Temporary Restraining Order, 1980 December (Box 2:22)
    - Hearing on Defendant's Motion and Order to Show Cause, 1980 December (Box 2:23)
    - Nobert and Bingham Affidavits, 1980 December (Box 2:24)
    - Motion to Suspend Injunction Court Papers, 1980 October (Box 2:25)
    - Defendant's Motion to Suspend Injunction, 1980 October (Box 2:26)
    - Temporary Injunctions, 1981 (Box 2:27)
    - Recusal of Judge Meskill, 1980 (Box 2:28)
    - Temporary Restraining Order, 1979-1980 (Box 2:29)
    - Decisions in Federal Court, 1980 (Box 2:30)
    - Plaintiff's Supplemental Brief, 1979 November 14 (Box 2:31)
    - Complaint, undated (Box 2:32)
    - Defendant's Motion to Dismiss, 1981 (Box 2:33)
    - Affidavits of Nobert, Gilbertson and Bingham, 1981 (Box 2:34)
    - Dismissal of WHS v. Maher, 1981 (Box 2:35)
    - Trial Transcripts, 1979-1981 (Box 2:36-88)
  - Research
    - Public Payment for Medical Expenses Before 1673, undated (Box 2:39)
    - Hospital Access, undated (Box 2:40)
    - Abortion Providers and Notices to Providers, undated (Box 2:41)
    - National Abortion Rights Action League, undated (Box 2:42)
    - Abortion Information, undated (Box 2:43)
    - Challenges to the Commissioner's Authority, undated (Box 2:44)
    - Connecticut Constitutional Convention, 1965 October 14 (Box 2:45)
    - Legislative Transcription, 1972 April 12 (Box 2:46)
- Series IV: Doe v. Maher, undated, 1981-1990
  - Court Documents
    - Application for Temporary Injunction, 1981 (Box 2:47)
    - Connecticut Supreme Court Appeal, 1981 (Box 2:48)
    - Class Certification, 1981 (Box 2:49)
    - Fictitious Name and Affidavit Brief, 1981 (Box 2:50)
    - Order of Service and Bond, 1981 (Box 2:51)
    - Memorandum of Decision and Orders, 1981 August 21 (Box 2:52)
    - Memorandum of Decision, 1981 October 9 (Box 2:53)
    - Affidavit of Doe, 1981 February 17 (Box 2:54)
    - Recuse of Judge Berdon, 1983 (Box 2:55)
    - Statute Authority to Cover Aboriton and Federal Financial Participation, 1981-1983 (Box 2:56)
    - Abortion Statutes, undated (Box 2:57)
    - Order to Show Cause, 1981 (Box 2:58)
    - Court Papers, 1983-1984 (Box 2:59)
    - Plaintiff's Third Request for Admission, 1985 (Box 2:60)
    - Plaintiff's First Request for Production, 1984 September 4 (Box 2:61)
    - Plaintiff's Second Request for Production, 1985 (Box 2:62-2:63)
    - Research of Connecticut Statutes and Equal Rights Amendment, n.d (Box 2:64)
    - Plaintiff's Fourth Request for Admission, 1985 (Box 2:65)
    - Doe v. Heintz, 1983 (Box 3:66)
    - Amendment to Complaint, 1983 (Box 3:67)
    - Memorandum of Law in Opposition to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss, 1983 (Box 3:68)
    - Subpoena for Deposition of Steven Heintz, 1984 (Box 3:69)
    - Contempt Papers, 1984 (Box 3:70)
    - Subsequent Pleadings, 1984 (Box 3:71)
    - Corrected Notice, 1984 (Box 3:72)
    - Memorandum of Decision and 120 Day Waiver, 1985 (Box 3:73)
    - Discovery Papers, 1984 March - 1985 April (Box 3:74-75)
    - Pretrial Conference, 1985 March 25 (Box 3:76)
    - Affidavit of Marshall Holley, M.D., 1981 (Box 3:77)
  - Plaintiff's Witnesses
    - Francis Baker, M.D., undated (Box 3:78)
    - Ann McLendon, M.D., undated (Box 3:79)
    - Ellen Frank, M.D., 1985 (Box 3:80)
    - Joan Babbott, M.D., undated (Box 3:81)
    - David Bingham, M.D., undated (Box 3:82)
    - Fred Naftolin, M.D., undated (Box 3:83)
    - Barbara Fibel, M.D., undated (Box 3:84)
    - Professor Christopher Collier, undated (Box 3:85)
  - Plaintiff's Exhibits
    - Exhibit List, undated (Box 3:86)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Provider Participation, undated (Box 3:87)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Hospital Inpatient Services, undated (Box 3:88)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Hospital Outpatient Services and Rates, undated (Box 3:89)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Skilled Nursing Facility, undated (Box 3:90)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Intermediate Care Facility, undated (Box 3:91)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Laboratory Services and Independent Radiology Centers, undated (Box 3:92)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Clinics, undated (Box 3:93)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Family Planning, Abortions and Hysterectomies, undated (Box 3:94)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Drugs, undated (Box 3:95)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Therapy Services and Physicians Services, undated (Box 3:96)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Psychiatrists and Podiatrists, undated (Box 3:97)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Vision Care Services, undated (Box 3:98)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Chiropractic/Naturopathic Services and Psychologists, undated (Box 3:99)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Private, Group Practice Dental Services and Home Health Services, undated (Box 3:100)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Medical Surgical Supplies and Durable Medical Equipment, undated (Box 3:101)
    - Exhibit G: CT Medical Services Policy-Orthotic, Prostethic Devices/Dialysis and School Based Child Health Services, undated (Box 3:102)
    - Exhibits 1-6,8-9,11,16-17 and Appendix, undated (Box 4:103)
    - Exhibits 22-30, undated, 1974-1985 (Box 4:104-111)
    - Exhibit 31-40, undated, 1977-1984 (Box 4:112-120)
    - Exhibit 42-50, undated, 1977, 1980-1985 (Box 4:121-129)
    - Exhibit 51-60, undated, 1979-1986 (Box 4:130-138)
    - Exhibit 61-70, undated, 1981-1985 (Box 4:139-148)
    - Exhibit 71-81, undated, 1977, 1980-85 (Box 4:149-154)
    - Exhibit 82-86, 1981-1985 (Box 4:155-157)
  - Defendant's Exhibits
    - Exhibits B and C, undated (Box 4:158)
  - Research
    - Court Injunction for CCAG v. Pugliese, 1984 (Box 5:159)
    - Stephen B. Heintz's article, "A Federalist Paper," 1983 (Box 5:160)
    - Chronology of Abortion and Medicaid Funds, 1966-1983 (Box 5:161)
    - Definition of Medical Necessity, 1981 (Box 5:162)
    - Court Documents for W.H.S. v Maher, 1979-1980 (Box 5:163)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1985 (Box 5:164)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 5:165)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 5:166)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 5:167)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 5:168)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 5:169)
    - Providers and DIM Reimbursement, 1984 (Box 5:170)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 5:171)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 5:172)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 5:173)
  - Depositions
    - Dennie Bothamley, 1984-1985 (Box 5:174)
    - Dennie Bothamley Deposition Notes, undated (Box 5:175)
    - Stephen B. Heintz, 1984-1985 (Box 5:176)
    - Exhibits B-E, G, I-N, 1984 (Box 5:177)
    - Exhibits U-X, AA, BB, 1984 (Box 5:178)
  - CT General Assistance Administration, 1980-1984 (Box 5:179)
  - Court Documents
    - Court Documents, 1986 April-May (Box 5:180)
    - Court Documents, 1986 June (Box 5:181)
    - Defendant's Appeal Papers, 1986 (Box 5:182)
    - Plaintiff's Appeal Papers, 1986 (Box 5:183)
    - Court Ordered Notices, 1986-1987 (Box 5:184)
    - Defendant's Appeal Brief, 1986 (Box 6:185)
    - Briefs on Temporary Injunction, 1981 (Box 6:186)
    - Court Documents, 1986-1989 (Box 6:187)
    - Court Documents, 1981 (Box 6:188)
    - Motion for Contempt, 1984-1986 (Box 6:189)
    - Court Documents, 1984-1985,1987 (Box 6:190)
    - Amicus Letters of Interest, 1986 (Box 6:191)
    - Court Orders and Rulings, 1988 (Box 6:192)
    - Plaintiff's Court Papers, 1988 (Box 6:193)
    - Defendant's Court Papers, 1988 (Box 6:194)
    - Defendant's Court Papers, 1989 (Box 6:195)
  - CT Informational Bulletins on Aborition Procedures and Payment, 1977-1981 (Box 6:196)
  - Newsclippings, 1984-1985 (Box 6:197)
  - Financial Costs to CCLU
    - Attorney Fee Calculations, 1981-1986 (Box 6:198)
    - Rosie Jiminez Memorial Alliance, 1986 (Box 6:199)
    - CCLU Doe v. Maher Costs, 1981-1985 (Box 6:200)
    - Claims Commission, 1987 (Box 6:201)
  - Chronology of Doe v. Maher, 1981-1986 (Box 6:202)
- Series V: Sheff v. O'Neill, undated, 1989-1998
  - Summary of Key Dates in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1992 (Box 7:202)
  - Plaintiff's Court Documents
    - 1989-1990 (Box 7:203-205)
    - 1991 (Box 7:206-207)
    - 1992 (Box 7:208-211)
    - 1993 (Box 7:212-218)
    - 1995 (Box 8:219-224)
  - Defendent's Court Documents
    - 1989-1990 (Box 8:225-227)
    - 1991 (Box 8:228-229)
    - 1992 (Box 8:230-235)
    - 1992 (Box 9:236-239)
    - 1993 (Box 9:240-244)
    - 1994 (Box 9:245-246)
    - 1995 (Box 9:247-249)
  - Court Orders, 1989-1996 (Box 9:250-251)
  - Court Calanders and Notices, 1981-1992, 1995 (Box 9:252)
  - Litigation Correspondence
    - 1989 (Box 10:253)
    - 1990 (Box 10:254)
    - 1991 (Box 10:255)
    - 1992 (Box 10:256-258)
    - 1993 (Box 10:259)
    - 1994 (Box 10:260)
    - 1995 (Box 10:261)
  - Intervenor's Court Papers, 1993, 1995, 2001 (Box 10:262-266)
  - Amicus Briefs
    - Master List, 1995 (Box 10:267)
    - Cities, 1995 (Box 10:268)
    - Civil Rights, 1995 (Box 10:269)
    - Education, 1995 (Box 10:270)
    - Law Professors, 1995 (Box 10:271)
    - Religous, 1995 (Box 10:272)
  - Research, Reports and Conferences
    - Current Legislation, 1992 (Box 11:273-274)
    - Legislative History, 1993 (Box 11:275-276)
    - Legislation, 1993 (Box 11:277)
    - Working Draft of an Act Concerning Magnet Schools, 1993 (Box 11:278)
    - State Department of Education Documents, 1993, 1995 (Box 11:279-280)
    - CABE Area Workshop on Quality Integrated Education Legislation, undated (Box 11:281)
    - Local Advisory Committee Reports, 1993-1994 (Box 11:282-284)
    - Final Reports of the Regional Forums, 1993-1994 (Box 11:285)
    - State Board of Education Meeting Minutes, 1993-1995 (Box 11:286-287)
    - School Construction Plans, 1988-1991 (Box 11:288-289)
    - Committee on Education Equity and Excellence, 1994 (Box 11:290-293)
    - Journal Articles on School Desegregation, 1988, 1991, 1993 (Box 12:294)
    - Bilingual Education, 1989-1993 (Box 12:295)
    - Magnet Schools, 1991-1993 (Box 12:296)
    - Early Childhood, 1990-1993 (Box 12:297)
    - Restructuring Education Systems, 1991-1993 (Box 12:298)
    - Tennessee's K-3 Class Size Study, 1985-1990 (Box 12:299)
    - General Articles on Remedy, 1988-1992 (Box 12:300)
    - Education Alternatives, Inc., 1994 (Box 12:301)
    - Regional Communities Cartoon, undated (Box 12:302)
    - Articles on Integration and Bilingual Education, undated (Box 12:303)
    - Articles on "Concentration of Poverty", 1975-1990 (Box 12:304-306)
    - Education Conferences, 1983, 1989-1992 (Box 12:307-308)
    - Effective Schools, 1989-1991 (Box 12:309)
    - Trinity College's President's Policy Forum, 1990 November 15 (Box 12:310)
    - Third Annual Conference on Demographic Diversity and Restructuring, 1991 May 29 (Box 12:311)
    - Hartford Graduate Center, 1988 September 28 (Box 12:312)
    - Institute for Teaching and Learning, 1989 May 1 (Box 12:313-314)
  - Court Cases
    - Lumpkin v. Meskill, 1972-1974, 1988, 1990-1991 (Box 13:315-319)
    - Alabama Coalition for Equity, Inc. v. Guy Hunt, 1992-1993,1997 (Box 13:320-322)
  - Reports from States Other than Connecticut
    - San Francisco's Orders and Plan, 1992-1993 (Box 13:323-325)
    - Colorado: Keyes v. School District Number One, 1985,1993 (Box 13:326)
    - Delaware's Desegregation, 1993 (Box 13:327)
    - Georgia: Armour v. Nix, 1975, 1977-1978 (Box 13:328-330)
    - Indiana: U.S. v. Board of School Commissioners of City of Indianapolis, 1982 (Box 13:331)
    - Wisconsin: Milwaukee Public School Desegregation, 1987, 1990 (Box 13:332-334)
    - Montana: Helena School District, 1985-1986, 1990 (Box 13:335-336)
    - Rhode Island: Controlled Choice Plan and Report of the 21st Century Education Commission, 1991-1992 (Box 14:337)
    - New York State's System of Public School Financing, 1987, 1993, 1995 (Box 14:338)
    - New Jersey: Public School Funding and Court Cases, 1975-1998 (Box 14:339-344)
  - Exhibits 1.0-5.22, undated (Box 14:345-356)
  - Exhibits 6.0-11.31, undated (Box 15:357-364)
  - Closing Arguments, 1994 November (Box 15:365-366)
  - Court Documents: Trial Transcripts
    - 1994 November 16 (Box 15:367)
    - 1994 September 18, 21 and June 1 (Box 15:368)
    - 1993 December 16 (Box 15:369)
    - 1993 December 16 (Box 15:370)
    - 1993 February 26 (Box 15:371)
    - 1993 February 11, 25 (Box 15:372)
    - 1993 January 8 (Box 15:373)
    - William M. Gordon, 1992 (Box 15:374)
    - 1993 February 25 (Box 16:375)
    - 1994 January 7, 8 (Box 16:376)
  - Meetings of the Governor's Commission on Quality and Integrated Education
    - 1990 January 4,16 and February 1 (Box 16:377)
    - 1990 March 1 (Box 16:378)
    - 1990 March 20, April 5, May 10 (Box 16:379)
    - 1990 June 7 (Box 16:380)
    - 1990 July 10 (Box 16:381)
    - 1990 August 22 and September 6 (Box 16:382)
    - 1990 October 4 (Box 16:383)
    - 1990 November 7 (Box 16:384)
    - 1990 December 13, 31 (Box 16:385)
    - H.C. Planning Consultants, Inc., 1989-1990 (Box 16:386)
    - 1989 October 12 (Box 16:387)
    - 1989 October 26 and November 9 (Box 16:388)
    - 1989 December 19 (Box 16:389-390)
  - Court Documents: Plaintiff's Case-in-Chief
    - 1992 December 31 (Box 17:391)
    - 1992 December 30 (Box 17:392-395)
    - 1992 December 29 (Box 17:396-397)
    - 1992 December 23 (Box 17:398)
    - 1992 December 23 (Box 17:399-400)
    - 1992 December 22 (Box 17:401-402)
    - 1992 December 21 (Box 17:403)
    - 1992 December 18 (Box 17:404-405)
    - 1992 December 17 (Box 17:406-407)
  - Court Documents
    - Plaintiff's Opening Arguement, 1992 December 16 (Box 17:408)
    - Partial Transcript From Plaintiff's Case-in-Chief, 1992 December 16 (Box 17:409)
    - Trial Transcript, 1993 January 28 (Box 17:410-411)
    - Plaintiff's Case-in-Chief, 1993 January 27 (Box 17:412-413)
    - Trial Transcripts, 1993 January 20-22 (Box 17:414-416)
    - Trial Transcript, 1993 January 15 (Box 17:417)
    - Trial Transcripts, 1993 January 12-14 (Box 18:418-420)
    - Trial Transcripts, 1993 January 6-8 (Box 18:421-425)
    - Trial Transcript, undated (Box 18:426-427)
    - Alphabetical Index of Witness Testimony, undated (Box 18:428)
    - Deposition of William Gordon, 1998 May-June (Box 18:429-431)
    - Deposition of David J. Armor,1993 February 23 (Box 18:432)
    - Plaintiff's Rebuttal, 1993 February 25 (Box 18:433)
    - Defendant's Case-in-Chief, 1993 February 18 (Box 18:434-435)
    - Trial Transcripts, 1993 February 17 (Box 18:436)
    - Defendant's Case-in-Chief, 1993 February 9 (Box 18:437-438)
    - Defendant's Case-in-Chief, 1993 February 5 (Box 18:439-440)
    - Defendant's Case-in-Chief, 1993 February 4 (Box 18:441-442)
    - Defendant's Case-in-Chief, 1993 February 3 (Box 18:443)
- Series VI: American Civil Liberties Union materials, undated, 1954-1981
  - Annual Report, 1959-1977 (Box 1:444)
  - Board Actions, 1981 (Box 1:445)
  - News, 1980 (Box 1:446)
  - Publications, undated (Box 1:447)
    - "ACLU-Let there be Law", 1971 (Box 1:448)
    - "What the WSJ says about the ACLU", 1965 (Box 1:449)
    - "Whose Civil Liberties?", 1954 (Box 1:450)
    - "The Working Parts", 1979 (Box 1:451)
  - Reports
    - "The Politics of Rights", undated (Box 1:452)
    - "The White Man's Navy", 1979 (Box 1:453)